Finding Aid for McCreery-Fenton Family papers 1818-1948
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
McCreery-Fenton Family papers 1818-1948 1860-1940
McCreery family.
85351 Aa 2, UAm
The McCreery and Fenton families were prominent Genesee county, Michigan residents some of whose members distinguished themselves in local and state government, as soldiers during the Civil War, and in the United States diplomatic service. Papers include diaries, correspondence and other material relating to the Civil War, local and state politics and aspects of diplomatic service in Central and South America.
12 linear feet in 13 boxes
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mr. Fenton McCreery Davison and came to the library in 1976. Donor no. 5868
The collection is open for research.
The McCreery and Fenton families were prominent Genesee county residents some of whose members distinguished themselves in local and state government, as soldiers during the Civil War, and in the United States diplomatic service.
William M. Fenton (1808-1871), for whom the city of Fenton, Michigan was named, was a lawyer, state senator (1846), lieutenant governor (1848, re-elected 1850), mayor of Flint (1858), and Democratic candidate for governor (1864). During the Civil War, although in his fifties, Fenton raised some of the first troops in the state. His initial appointment was as major in the 7th Michigan Infantry. He later transferred to command of the 8th Michigan Infantry. In 1863, he was discharged with the rank of colonel.
His son-in-law, William B. McCreery (1836-1896), also served in the Civil War. As colonel in the 21st Michigan Infantry, McCreery was wounded and captured at the Battle of Chickamauga (1863) and imprisoned for a time at Libby Prison, but escape with others through the famous tunnel. After the war, he became involved in public service. He was mayor of Flint (1865) and state treasurer (1875-1879). He later was selected to be United States Consul to Chile. During his period of service (1890-1891), relations with Chile were difficult as the country underwent a revolution against the Balmaceda administration. There was an attack on U.S. sailors, sometime referred to as the "Baltimore Affairs" that threatened to bring the United States into a war with Chile.
Assisting McCreery in Chile was his son Fenton R. McCreery (1866-1940) whose subsequent diplomatic career would take him to different countries of Central and South America. Graduating from the Michigan Military Academy in 1888, he accepted assignment with his father as a clerk in the United States consulate in Valparaiso, Chile (1890-1891). Fenton was later appointed secretary of the legation in Santiago (1891-1893), serving as chargé d'affaires for four months. Subsequent assignment included posts as secretary of the legation and embassy and chargé d'affaires in Mexico (1897-1906), minister resident and consul general in the Dominican Republic (1907), envoy extraordinary and minister plenipotentiary in Honduras (1909-1911) and military attaché ©n Brazil (1919). Fenton, additionally, served as an advisor to a senate subcommittee on foreign relations investigating Mexican affairs (1912-1913). He also lectured widely on Latin American affairs. During World War I, he served in Europe with the Red Cross.
The McCreery Family papers is an accumulation of family materials covering a period of more than a century. The collection is arranged primarily by the name of family member.
The McCreery-Fenton family collection documents the individual careers of family members who served their community and their nation in a variety of roles. Through correspondence, diaries and other materials, the researcher will find information pertaining to the Civil War, to the history of Flint and Fenton in Genesee County, Michigan, and to facets of America's diplomatic relations with some of the countries of Central and South America. Arranged by name of the three principal family members represented in the collection - William M. Fenton, William B. McCreery, and Fenton R. McCreery, the papers also include series of general family materials, business records, and photographs.
Diaries.; Bryan, William Jennings, 1860-1925.; Chickamauga, Battle of, Ga., 1863.; United States--Foreign relations--Chile.; Chile--Foreign relations--United States.; Democratic Party (Mich.); United States--Foreign relations--Dominican Republic.; Dominican Republic--Foreign relations--United States.; Fenton (Mich.); Fenton family.; Flint (Mich.); Fredericksburg (Va.), Battle of, 1862.; Genesee County (Mich.); United States--Foreign relations--Honduras.; Honduras--Foreign relations--United States.; Latin America.; Libby Prison.; McCreery family.; Mexico--Foreign relations--United States.; Michigan Military Academy.; Michigan--Politics and government--1845-1860.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1841-1850.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1851-1860.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1861-1870.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1871-1880.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1881-1890.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1891-1900.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1901-1910.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1911-1920.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1921-1930.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1931-1940.; Michigan. Supreme Court.; Presidents--United States--Election--1896.; Silver question.; United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 7th (1861-1865); United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 8th (1861-1865); United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 21st (1862-1865); United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States--Politics and government--1845-1861.
Subjects - Visual
Bedrooms--Michigan--Flint--1883.; California.; Chattanooga (Tenn.), Battle of, 1863.; Children.; Chile.; Diplomats.; Fenton, William M., 1808-1871.; Streets--Michigan--Flint.; Honduras.; Interiors--Michigan--Flint--1883.; Lookout Mountain (Tenn.), Battle of, 1863.; McCreery, Fenton R. (Fenton Reuben), 1866-1940.; McCreery, William B. (William Barker), 1836-1896.; Mexico.; Missouri.; New Mexico.; Theaters--Michigan--Flint.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Women.
Contributors:
Begole, Josiah Williams, 1815-1896.; Belknap, Charles Eugene, 1846-1929.; Blair, Austin, 1818-1894.; Bliss, Aaron Thomas, 1837-1906.; Cass, Lewis, 1782-1866.; Clayton, Powell, 1833-1914.; Crapo, Henry Howland, 1804-1869.; Díaz, Porfirio, 1830-1915.; Egan, Patrick.; Fenton, William M., 1808-1871.; Goodrich, Enos, 1813-1897.; Grew, Joseph C. (Joseph Clark), 1880-1965.; Hall, Charles P.; Hay, John, 1838-1905.; Knox, Philander C. (Philander Chase), 1853-1921.; McCreery, Fenton R. (Fenton Reuben), 1866-1940.; McCreery, William B. (William Barker), 1836-1896.; Pepper, Charles Melville, 1859-1930.; Putnam, Herbert, 1861-1955.; Rich, John Treadway, 1841-1926.; Ridgely, Benjamin H., 1861-1908.; Robertson, Jno. (John), 1814-1887.; Rosencrans, William Starke, 1819-1898.; Schley, Winfield Scott, 1839-1911.; Sheridan, George Augustus, 1840-1896.; Sherman, John, 1823-1900.; Taliaferro, James Piper, 1847-1934.; Taylor, George Washington, 1849-; Thomas, George Henry, 1816-1870.; Ward, Eber Brock, d. 1873.; Wilcox, Orland B.
Genre/Form:
Albumen prints.; Cabinet card photographs.; Photographs.; Stereographs.; Tintypes.
- William M. Fenton 1842-1871
  The William M. Fenton series (1842-1871; .5 linear feet) consists primarily of documentation of his Civil War career, but only scant materials about his political activities. Of interest in addition to correspondence and official documents is a record book from the 8th Michigan Infantry that he maintained. The volume is dated 1861-1862. Fenton also collected other 8th Michigan Infantry related papers such as the diary of Captain Horatio Belcher pertaining to the Fredericksburg campaign. Correspondents in this series include Austin Blair, Lewis Cass, Enos Goodrich, and Eber Brock Ward.
  - Correspondence undated, 1842-1843, 1853-1871, 4 folders (Box 1)
    (Folders nos. 1-4)
  - 7th Michigan Infantry papers 1861 (Box 1)
    (Folder no. 5)
  - 8th Michigan Infantry papers 1861 (Box 1)
    (Folder no. 6)
  - 8th Michigan Infantry record book 1861-1862 (Box 1)
    (Folder no. 6-a)
  - Ninth Army Corps papers (Box 1)
    (Folder no. 7)
  - 8th Michigan Infantry discharge papers 1863 (Box 1)
    (Folder no. 8)
  - 8th Michigan Infantry miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (Folder nos. 9-10)
  - Newsclippings (Box 1)
    (Folder no. 11)
  - Diary (7 p.) of a campaign in Virginia (Fredericksburg) by Captain Horatio Belcher, 8th Michigan, 1862 (Box 1)
    (Folder no. 12)
  - Address by Charles McCreery at 1st reunion of the 8th Michigan Infantry 1867 (Box 1)
    (Folder no. 13)
  - Reunion miscellanea, including reminiscences presented posthumously 1903 (Box 1)
    (Folder no. 14)
  - Miscellanea (Box 1)
    (Folder no. 15)
  - Newsclippings, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (Folders nos. 16-17)
  - Masonic funeral service 1871 (Box 1)
    (Folder no. 18)
  - Record book of sundry agencies and collections 1855-1870, 1 volumes (Box 1)
- William B. McCreery 1854-1896, 1 linear feet
  The William B. McCreery series (1854-1896; 1 linear ft.) consists of correspondence, Civil War documents, and miscellaneous pertaining largely to his war service and to his time as a diplomat in Chile in the 1890s. Some of McCreery's correspondents include Josiah W. Begole, Charles E. Belknap, Austin Blair, Henry H. Crapo, Patrick Egan, John T. Rich, John Robertson, William S. Rosencrans, Winfield S. Schley, George A. Sheridan, and Orland B. Wilcox.
  - Correspondence undated, 1860-1896, 23 folders (Box 1)
    (Folders nos. 19-41)
  - Papers concerning politics and religion 1854 (Box 1)
    (Folder no. 42)
  - Certificates of Civil War service 1862-1864 (Box 1)
    (Folder no. 43)
  - Papers concerning his presumed death at the Battle of Chickamauga and later discharge from the army 1863-1864 (Box 1)
    (Folder no. 44)
  - Miscellanea concerning operations of the 21st Michigan Infantry 1863-1864, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (Folder nos. 45-46)
  - Papers concerning reunions of the 21st Michigan Infantry 1889-1929 (Box 1)
    (Folder no. 47)
  - Speech concerning escape from Libby Prison 1889 (published in 1893), including newspaper clippings about the escape (Box 1)
    (Folder no. 48)
  - Scrapbook concerning 21st Michigan Infantry and the escape of McCreery and others from Libby Prison, 1 volumes (Box 1)
  - Speech concerning General George H. Thomas, Commander of the Army of the Cumberland 1895 (Box 2)
    (Folder no. 49)
  - Papers concerning mining interest 1895 (Box 2)
    (Folder no. 50)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    (Folder no. 51)
  - Miscellanea (Box 2)
    (Folder no. 52)
  - Papers concerning the death of William B. McCreery (Box 2)
    (Folder no. 53)
  - Civil War miscellanea, 2 folders (Box 2)
    (Folder nos. 54-55)
  - Scrapbook regarding Republican Party county conventions and McCreery's campaign for state treasurer 1874, 1 volumes (Box 2)
  - Bank book from Chile 1890-1891, 1 volumes (Box 2)
- Fenton R. McCreery 1875-1940, 4.5 linear feet
  The Fenton R. McCreery series (1875-1940; 4.5 linear feet) contains correspondence and diaries. McCreery was a keen observer of the passing scene and a diligent recorder of the events in his own life. His diaries are detailed and well-written accounts of his diplomatic service, his various travels, hunting sojourns, and World War I activities. Some of the earliest notebooks and diaries cover the period of his education at the Michigan Military Academy. Among Fenton McCreery's correspondents are Aaron T. Bliss, Powell Clayton, Porfirio Diaz, Patrick Egan, Joseph C. Grew, Charles P. Hall, John Hay, Philander C. Knox, Charles M. Pepper, Herbert Putnam, John T. Rich, Benjamin H. Ridgely, John Sherman, James P. Taliaferro, and George W. Taylor.
  - Correspondence undated, 1875-1904, 23 folders (Box 2)
    (Folder nos. 56-78)
  - Correspondence 1905-1940, 10 folders (Box 3)
    (Folder nos. 79-88)
  - Miscellaneous papers regarding Latin America (Box 3)
    (Folder no. 89)
  - Chile
    - Scrapbook 1890-1891, 1 volumes (Box 3)
    - Notes concerning the Chilean Revolution and the "Baltimore" affair 1891-1892 (Box 3)
      (Folder no. 90)
    - Newspaper clippings concerning the Chilean Revolution and the "Baltimore" affair (Box 3)
      (Folder no. 91)
    - Miscellanea, 2 folders (Box 3)
      (Folder nos. 92-93)
    - Notes on Chile and Peru (mostly travel accounts) (Box 3)
      (Folder no. 94)
  - Mexico
    - Notes on political conditions circa 1900 (Box 3)
      (Folder no. 95)
    - Drafts of speeches and letters; and miscellaneous notes (Box 3)
      (Folder no. 96)
    - Speeches (Box 3)
      (Folder no. 97)
    - Corrections for Carlton Beals' biography of Porfirio Diaz (Box 3)
      (Folder no. 98)
    - Newsclippings (Box 3)
      (Folder no. 99)
    - Miscellanea, 2 folders (Box 3)
      (Folder nos. 100-101)
  - Dominican Republic
    - Papers 1907-1909 (Box 3)
      (Folder no. 102)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 3)
      (Folder no. 103)
  - Honduras
    - Papers 1909-1911 (Box 3)
      (Folder no. 104)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 3)
      (Folder no. 105)
  - Papers concerning Cuba and Central America (Box 3)
    (Folder no. 106)
  - Papers concerning Brazil 1919 (Box 3)
    (Folder no. 107)
  - Notes on service with the Red Cross in Europe 1915-1916 (Box 3)
    (Folder no. 108)
  - Notes and draft of speech on Court of International Justice 1925 (Box 3)
    (Folder no. 109)
  - Translation of "The Bird in Snow" of Armando Palacio Valdez (Box 3)
    (Folder no. 110)
  - Papers concerning the U.S. Chamber of Commerce (including speeches) 1938-1940 (Box 4)
    (Folder no. 111)
  - Notes on the history of Genesee County and aspect of American history (Box 4)
    (Folder no. 112)
  - Miscellaneous papers (Box 4)
    (Folder no. 113)
  - Newspaper clippings, 2 folders (Box 4)
    (Folder nos. 114-115)
  - Letters of sympathy on death of Fenton R. McCreery 1940 (Box 4)
    (Folder no. 116)
  - Michigan Military Academy notebook containing sick list and punishment lists 1882, 1 volumes (Box 4)
  - Diaries
    - 1881-1882, 1 volumes (Box 4)
    - 1882, 1 volumes (Box 4)
      (hunting trip)
    - April-May 1886 (Box 4)
      (trip to Central America)
    - July 1886-February 1887 (Box 4)
    - August 1886-May 1887 (Box 4)
      (Microfilm copy available)
    - November 1887-February 1888 (Box 4)
    - April-June 1890 (Box 4)
    - January 1891, March-November 1891 (Box 4)
    - December 1891, December 1892 (Box 4)
    - 1891-1893 (Box 4)
      (labeled Adelaide McCreery, but more probably Fenton R. McCreery)
    - 1895 (Box 4)
    - 1896 (Box 4)
    - 1897 (Box 4)
    - February-September 1898 (Box 4)
    - October 1898-September 1899 (Box 4)
    - May-June 1899 (Box 4)
    - September 1899-March 1900 (Box 4)
    - March 1900-May 1900 (Box 4)
    - June-December 1900 (Box 4)
    - December 1900-June 1901 (Box 4)
    - June-September 1901 (Box 4)
    - December 1901-August 1902 (Box 4)
    - August 1902-September 1903 (Box 4)
    - September 1903-March 1904 (Box 4)
    - March 1904-1905 (Box 5)
    - January 1906-September 1907 (Box 5)
    - September 1906-November 1906 (Box 5)
    - January 1908-May 1909 (Box 5)
    - July 1909-February 1911 with scattered entries for, March 1904-1926 (Box 5)
      (microfilm copy available)
    - March-August 1910 (Box 5)
    - February-September 1911 (Box 5)
    - May-June 1911 (Box 5)
    - February-August 1913 (Box 5)
    - February-May 1913 (Box 5)
    - January-May 1917 (Box 5)
    - July 1917 (Box 5)
    - January-March 1918 (Box 5)
    - March-April 1918 (Box 5)
    - July-December 1919 (Box 5)
    - November 1918-June 1919 (Box 5)
    - June 1920, September 1926 (Box 5)
    - January 1920-May 1921 (Box 5)
    - May-December 1921 (Box 5)
    - 1922-February 1924 (Box 5)
    - March-September 1924 (Box 5)
    - October 1924-May 1926 (Box 5)
    - June-July 1926 (Box 6)
    - 1927 (Box 6)
    - 1928-July 1929 (Box 6)
    - July 1929-October 1929 (Box 6)
    - October 1929-1930 (Box 6)
    - 1931 (Box 6)
    - January-November 1932 (Box 6)
    - December 1932-May 1933 (Box 6)
    - May 1933-December 1934 (Box 6)
    - 1935-April 1936 (Box 6)
    - April 1936-May 1937 (Box 6)
    - May-December 1937 (Box 6)
  - Scrapbook of FRM while a student at the Michigan Military Academy 1878-1882, 1 volumes (Box 6)
  - Department of State volume of documents relating to the Baltimore affair and U.S. relations with Chile (Box 6)
  - Scrapbook 1911-1916, 1 volumes (Box 7)
  - Notebooks, diary fragments, etc., 8 volumes in 1 expandable folder folders (Box 7)
- McCreery- Fenton family materials 1818-1948, 1 linear feet
  The McCreery-Fenton family series (1818-1948; 1 linear ft.) includes materials of other family members. There is a diary of a trip to Europe in 1873 by Sarah R. Fenton, travel diaries of Adelaide Fenton McCreery while touring in South America, especially Chile, and scattered letters of Ada B. McCreery. Here will also be found information on Flint and Fenton local history.
  - Biographical data concerning the McCreery and Fenton families (Box 7)
  - Early papers, including South Carolina land transactions (Box 7)
  - Birdsall family letters 1829, 1832, 1858 (Box 7)
  - Fenton family correspondence 1850-1859 (Box 7)
  - Fenton family miscellanea (Box 7)
  - Reuben McCreery letters 1863, 1868 (Box 7)
  - Ada B. McCreery
    - Correspondence undated (Box 7)
    - Correspondence 1855-1884 (Box 7)
    - Order of services at funeral 1884 (Box 7)
  - Genevieve Decker McCreery correspondence 1891-1899 (Box 7)
  - Matthew and Katherine (McCreery) Davison correspondence 1898-1948 (Box 7)
  - McCreery family miscellanea (Box 7)
  - Papers concerning Fenton, Michigan (Box 7)
  - Papers concerning Flint, Michigan (Box 7)
  - Papers concerning Masonic Order (Box 7)
  - Papers concerning the election of 1896, the visit of William Jennings Bryan to Michigan and the Free Silver issue (Box 7)
  - Unidentified correspondence (Box 7)
  - Unidentified and fragmentary papers, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Joseph B. Fenton Michigan Supreme Court register 1838-1842, 1 volumes (Box 7)
  - Sarah R. Fenton diary of European trip 1873 (Box 7)
  - Adelaide Fenton McCreery diary of trip to Chile January-February 1892 (Box 7)
  - Fenton Block account book 1874-1891 (Box 7)
  - Chancery register - Genesee County 1855-1858 (Box 7)
- Business records and miscellaneous
  - Land indentures, legal documents, business correspondence, student notebooks, published material, ephemera (Box 11)
  - Land indentures, legal documents, business correspondence, student notebooks, published material, ephemera (Box 12)
    (continued)
  - Land indentures, legal documents, business correspondence, student notebooks, published material, ephemera (Box 13)
- Photographs
  The Photograph series (2 linear ft.) includes images of the family and taken by family members. There is also a subseries of commercially produced photographs and stereographs from the period of the Civil War and others collected as a result of Fenton McCreery's diplomatic service in Latin America.
  - Personal
    - Fenton, William M., also includes steel engraving (Box 8)
    - Flint, Michigan (street views; veterans activities) (Box 8)
      (also oversize folder UAm)
    - Flint, Michigan (bedroom) (Box 8)
    - Groups (women; professional meetings) (Box 8)
    - Honduras (Box 8)
    - Individuals (identified) (Box 8)
    - Individuals (unidentified)
      - Children (Box 8)
      - Men (Box 8)
      - Women, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - McCreery, Fenton
      - Early photographs (as infant and young man) (Box 8)
      - Portraits (Box 8)
      - Portraits (World War I era) (Box 8)
      - Later photographs (portraits and with others) (Box 8)
      - Latin American diplomatic service (group photographs, embassy buildings, photos of countryside), 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Friends and colleagues (Box 8)
      - Travel and family photos circa 1925-1940 (Box 8)
      - Local views (including snow and flood photos) (Box 8)
    - McCreery, William (Box 8)
    - Tintypes of family members (Box 9)
      (includes Civil War soldiers, boys in baseball suits, etc.)
  - Commercial photographs and stereographs
    (collected from period of the Civil War and as a result of Fenton McCreery's diplomatic service and other travels)
    - California (Buena Vista home and views) (Box 9)
    - Chile (Box 9)
    - China (Box 9)
    - Civil War (Box 9)
      (portraits and group views, many of them relating to the Battle of Chattanooga)
    - Egypt (Box 9)
    - Europe, 3 folders (Box 9)
    - Indians (Box 10)
    - Latin American subjects (Box 10)
    - Mexico (buildings and views) (Box 10)
    - Mexico - Lower California (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 10)
    - Missouri (Box 10)
    - New Mexico (Box 10)
    - United States (views of tourist sites)